A Guide to the Papers of Edwin M. Watson and of Frances Nash Watson, 9786
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Edwin M. Watson and of Frances Nash Watson bulk 1933-1945
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9786
This collection is 21 feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Many of the papers in this archive came from General Watson's office in the White House, and were turned over to Mrs. Watson after her husband's death. Added to these were his personal papers; the archive was moved to "Kenwood," the Watson's home near Charlottesville, Virginia, where it remained until Mrs. Watson's death in December 1971. In her will, Mrs. Watson bequested the entire contents of the files to the University of Virginia, and the files were delivered to the Library in the spring of 1972.
Biographical/Historical Information
Edwin Martin Watson was born in Eufala, Alabama, 10 December 1883, but moved while very young to Martinsville, Virginia where he grew up and received his early education. He received an appointment to the United States Military Academy and graduated in the Class of 1908. Commissioned a second lieutenant in the infantry he saw service in various posts in the United States and in the Phillipine Islands. After a tour as military aide to President Woodrow Wilson, Captain Watson transferred to the artillery. He served with distinction in the A.E.F. in France, winning a number of combat decorations. During the Versailles negotiations he served as junior aide to President Wilson, and returned to Washington in that capacity. He married Frances Nash, a promising concert pianist, in 1920. Two years in France at various French field artillery schools followed, and then various tours in U.S. artillery posts. In June, 1927, Major Watson graduated from the Command and General Staff School at Fort Leavenworth, and was ordered to the American Embassy in Brussels as Military Attache, serving there for four years. Returning to the United States in 1931, Watson served with an artillery unit in New York, was promoted to lieutenant colonel, and in January, 1933, reported to the General Staff in Washington. On June 1, 1933, he was ordered as Military Aide to President Roosevelt. By 1939, Watson was a brigadier general, and secretary to the President; he was promoted to Major General on October 1, 1940. He died suddenly during the return trip from the Yalta Conference on 20 February 1945.
Scope and Content Information
This collection, which fills fifty-one Hollinger storage boxes occupying about twenty-one linear feet of shelving, consists of the papers of Major General Edwin M. Watson, and of his wife, Frances Nash Watson. The material covers the period 1900 (1933)-(1945) 1967. Included is a good deal of material from General Watson's army career and personal life, but the largest portion of the material was produced by his service as military aide to President Franklin D. Roosevelt from 1933-1939, and subsequently, as secretary to Roosevelt until Watson's death in February 1945. Official files of various sorts kept by General Watson during this service are included. However, as he was a personal friend of President Roosevelt, there is much material of an unofficial nature such as humorous memoranda, photographs taken on vacation and official trips, mementoes, etc. Mrs. Watson's papers fall into two groups. The first consists of papers re General Watson's death and funeral, letters of condolence, etc., while the second is largely made up of an extensive correspondence with Supreme Court Justice Felix Frankfurter. Also included is a letter from Albert Einstein about national defense or the atomic bomb (Box 10).
Organization
After General Watson's death, Mrs. Watson, and his secretary, Mrs. Lillian Dennison, worked with General Watson's papers for many months. It is impossible now to determine the integrity of the files, or the original organization. But the series found when the papers reached the Library were retained for two reasons: they are logical, and a card index to the files had been prepared which was keyed to this organization. Considerable material was received, particularly many of General Watson's personal papers and all of Mrs. Watson's, which had not been organized at all. In many cases, however, some indications of the intent of the original organizers were apparent, and these indications have been followed wherever possible.
Mrs. Watson prepared an "Explanation of File" which was dated 21 April 1947. Each series is described, and these descriptions have been incorporated in the Series-Container listing which follows. Through Box 39 the comments on each series are those of Mrs. Watson except for material in brackets which has been supplied by the compiler of this Guide. The description and organization of the material in Boxes 40-51, and of the oversize and other material was prepared by the compiler.
Mrs. Watson wrote the following introduction to the papers in her "Explanation of File":
April 21, 1947
This is a file of Major General Edwin Martin Watson.
Some of these documents concern his early life, others relate to West Point days and his military career, but most of them pertain to his part in President Roosevelt's administration-first, as his Military Aide, and later as Secretary to the President, while continuing his duties as Military Aide.
These written records indicate the nature and scope of General Watson's duties, and are evidence of his influence in the President's Life - officially and personally. Much, of course, was never put on paper, but something of this can be read between the lines of many of the General's remarkable memos and letters.
The arrangement of the papers tell the story of General Watson's daily activities - somewhat in the order of events as they occurred, as follows.
Card Index
Other Finding Aid
The card index file, which is available upon request, consists of about 4,000 cards. There is a card, or a series of cards, for every person with whom General Watson corresponded and there are many subject cards. There is an entry on each correspondent's card for each piece of correspondence with its date and a description of the content of each letter in a short phrase. The index, as far as can be determined, covers the material in Boxes 1 through 39. It is presumed that this card index was begun during General Watson's White House Service to enable him to locate any items in his files, but there is no definite evidence to support this presumption. The personal papers, which were received unorganized, were not included in the index, nor were Mrs. Watson's papers.
Contents List
- Memos to General Watson 1933-1945
  Beginning in 1933 and continuing to 1945, these memos record General Watson's personal appointment; requests from the President's other Secretaries; from Mrs. Roosevelt or her secretary (Malvina Thompson, formerly Mrs. Scheider); from the General's own secretaries, his liaison officers with the War Department; and lesser members of the White House personnel. These memos and their attached papers cover practically every phase of his daily activities.
  Correspondence and Memos not entered in Gen. Watson's files.
  - 1933-1939 Oct. (Box 1)
  - 1939 November-1940 December (Box 2)
  - 1940 July - 1940 December (Box 3)
  - 1941 July - 1941 June (Box 4)
  - 1941 July - 1942 January 1-14 (Box 5)
  - 1942 January 15-31 - 1942 December (Box 6)
  - 1943 January - 1943 December (Box 7)
  - 1944 January - 1945 January
- Reminders to EMW from EMW March, 1939-1942
  The General had an ingenious trick of writing memos to himself, starting out "Memo to General Watson" and signed "EMW," which served to remind him of any matter he wanted brought to his attention. He seldom needed the reminder but it was always there in the background, just as a check-up.
  - March 1939 - 1942 (Box 9)
- Memos to the President 1935-1944
  These memos, mainly from General Watson, were in answer to questions of the President, or brought up subjects General Watson thought he might wish or should consider. They dealt with matters both high and low - from important secret papers to jokes on General Watson; included questions asked the President by Senators and Congressmen, letters brought to the President's attention by Mrs. Roosevelt, etc.
  Many of these memos are very revealing, characteristic of General Watson - and give a good indication of his personal and official relationship with the President.
  Memos to the President Apparently Never Filed.
  - 1935 - 1939 April (Box 9)
  - 1939 May - 1940 January (Box 10)
  - 1940 February - 1944 (Box 11)
- Memos from the President 1935 - Sept. 1944
  These deal with correspondence; requests from the President; various jobs he wanted done; politics; directives, and so on. Some are formal memos, others just a note jotted on top of a letter by the President's secretary, at his direction, "Pa, to answer," "Pa, tell them I cannot do this."
  Memos from the President Apparently never filed.
  - 1935 - 1940 January (Box 12)
  - 1940 March - 1944 September (Box 13)
- President's Memos (Original) 1935 - 1941
  These papers all carry the President's handwriting, usually are from the President to General Watson; some are corrections or notations in the President's hand. Most of these memos are in a serious or official vein - as distinguished from the next section of the file, President's Witticisms (Original).
  - 1935-1940 (Box 14)
  - 1940 - 1944 (Box 15)
- President's Witticisms (Original) [1935-1944]
  These are not all witticisms, as some of the papers strike rather a grim note - but they include quips, puns, jokes on General Watson, as well as some originated by the General on others. Each has a note or memo in the President's handwriting.
  - 1935 - 1939 (Box 15)
  - 1939 - 1944 (Box 16)
- President's Appointment Memos April 1939 - December 1941
  These are memos from General Watson usually to members of his staff, directing that one person or another be placed on the appointment list of the President. They formed the background information for the Daily Schedule.
  - 1939 April - 1942 (Box 16)
- Daily Schedule (Original) [President's: December 1939 - January 1945]
  These are the "draft" copies of the President's daily appointment list, prepared by General Watson the Day before and submitted to the President each morning at the bedside Conference.
  The President's handwriting is on most [some] of these lists - adding, changing, deleting, sometimes writing an entire new schedule, but more often just shuffling the hours 5 minutes one way or another. The President did this to tease the General - and it became quite a game with him.
  - [1939-1941 Memoranda of Future Engagements for the President] (Box 17)
  - 1939 [December] to 1941 February (Box 17)
  - 1941 March - November (Box 19)
  - 1941 December (Box 19)
    [1941 Daily schedules of the President apparently never filed]
  - 1942 August - 1943 May (Box 20)
  - 1943 June - 1944 February (Box 21)
  - 1944 March - 1945 January (Box 22)
- Elections & Inaugurations
  This section includes letters to and from people in all walks of life about President Roosevelt's four elections and inaugurations. The bulk of the correspondence, of course, concerns the third term.
  [folders for 1933, 1936, 1940(3), 1944, and a folder headed "Inaugural Gala, 1941"]
  - 1933-1945 (Box 23)
- The Supreme Court (Box 24)
  This is a rather scanty section of the file and contains letters to and from several of the Supreme Court Justices; namely, [Douglas, Frankfurter, Jackson, and Reed - personal correspondence].
- The Cabinet (Box 24)
  This section contains correspondence with practically all of the President's Cabinet members.
  Of course, many letters from these officials are attached to MEMO and will be found in that group - (for individual names or subjects, see the card index file).
  [Includes folders for Harry H. Woodring, Henry A. Wallace Frank C. Walker, Henry L. Stimson, Edward R. Stettinius, Daniel C. Roper, Frances Perkins, Frank Murphy, Henry Morganthau, Jesse Jones, Robert Jackson, Harold Ickes, Cordell Hull, Francis Biddle, and James A. Farley. Chiefly personal correspondence with a few photographs and "official" papers.]
- Administration
  Letters to and from "below Cabinet status" members of President Roosevelt's administration; this section also includes his Secretaries, his Naval Aides, the Governors, and such officials; also Honorable Bernard M. Baruch in his status as Adviser to the President; the White House office force, etc. The Secret Service comes in here. [Alphabetical arrangement of folders for such persons as Bernard Baruch, Jonathan Daniels, Josephus Daniels, Stephen T. Early, J. Edgar Hoover, Louis Johnson, Fiorello LaGuardia, Nelson Rockefeller, etc. Chiefly personal with some "official" papers.]
  - B. M. Baruch - Josehus Daniels (Box 24)
  - Joseph Davis - Geo. T. Messersmith (Box 25)
  - Gov. M. M. Neely - Stanley Woodward (Box 26)
- Legislation (Box 26)
  Correspondence with Senators and Congressmen. However, a great many of the letters from these gentlemen are filed under REQUESTS, are attached to various MEMOS, or with the ELECTION AND INAUGURUATIONS section. (The card index will locate these under the names of the individual officials.). [Alphabetical arrangement of folders for individual senators followed by folders for Congressmen.]
- Requests: [1933-1945]
  Everybody asked for something - for commissions in the Army or Navy; retired officers desired active duty; requests for jobs, deferment, autographs, photographs, information; classmates wanted promotion, or appointment as Inspector General, Surgeon General, Quartermaster General; requests for appointments to West Point and to the Naval Academy; for the pens used by the President in signing bills; requests made through Mrs. Roosevelt and her secretary Miss Malvina Thompson (the former Mrs. Scheider). This gives but a scant idea of the volume of requests which went through General Watson's hands. In the card index there is also a REQUESTS card which shows various requests attached to MEMOS, etc.
  - 1933-1939 February (Box 26)
  - 1939 March - 1941 August (Box 27)
  - 1942 January - 1945 and undated (Box 28)
- Military
  [Alphabetical arrangement of correspondence with military officers, chiefly West Point classmates and friends. Includes Jonathan Wainwright and George S. Patton, Jr.]
  - Class of 1906 [West Point] - Patton, Geo. S. (Box 28)
  - Haig Shekerjian - Z (Box 29)
- [Miscellaneous] (Box 29)
- [Intelligence] (Box 29)
- [World War 2] (Box 29)
- Advice and Suggestions (Box 29)
  This section includes crank letters, as well as constructive criticism and suggestions.
- Press and Radio (Box 30)
  9 folders of correspondence with reporters, or re articles on Watson.
- Invitations to E.M.W. 1933-1944 (Box 31)
  Chronological arrangement.
- Trips - F.D.R.
  Chronological arrangement of folders containing, notes, memos, photographs, etc., 1933-1945, including copies of Gen. Watson's authorizations for expenses on these trips.
  - 1933-1937 (Box 32)
  - 1938-1943 April (Box 33)
  - 1943 July - 1945 (Box 34)
    Photographs of Quebec and Pacific Trips, 1944
- Roosevelt Family - Misc. (Box 35)
- Miscellaneous Files (Box 35)
  Includes folders re autograph requests, cigars and liquors, household furnishings, etc.
- Personal Files
  - Australia - Sweden (Box 36)
  - Artists (Box 36)
  - Army phas brief alphabetical arrangement of folders for prominent people like Geo. C. Marshall, Douglas MacArthur, etc.] (Box 36)
  - Served with or Under (Box 36)
  - Wreaths (Box 28)
  - A (Box 38)
  - Colored People (Box 38)
  - Liaison Officers with War Department (Box 38)
  - Court-Martial and Class B Cases [submitted to the President for review and sent to Watson for his recommendations] (Box 38)
  - A-E (Box 38)
  - F-Z (Box 39)
- Edwin M. Watson: Personal Papers Found Unorganized
  These files have been arranged alphabetically by the subject headings found on the folders.
  - Address Book of E.M.W. (Box 40)
  - Ambassadorship Story 1939 (Box 40)
  - Bets 1934-1944 (Box 40)
  - Biographical data & correspondence re 1939-1944 (Box 40)
  - Biographical data & correspondence re 1939-1944 (Box 40)
  - Biography - Gen. Watson
  - Material re service in Brussels, Belgium as Military Attache 1927-1933 (Box 40)
  - Charlottesville, Virginia and "Kenwood" (Box 40)
  - Chickens and Eggs (Box 40)
  - Clothes 1934-1944
  - Clubs and Societies (Box 40)
    - Clubs and Societies - General 1934-1944 (Box 40)
    - Alfalfa and Army and Navy Clubs (Box 40)
    - Chevy Chase Club (Box 40)
    - Cincinnati, Society of (Box 40)
    - Colonnade Club and Farmington Country Club (Box 41)
    - Jefferson Island Club (Box 41)
    - Metropolitan Club and Phi Delta Theta (Box 41)
  - Congratulations (Box 41)
    - Congratulatory letters to E.M.W.: A-F (Box 41)
    - Congratulatory letters to E.M.W.: H-P (Box 41)
    - Congratulatory letters to E.M.W.: Q-Z (Box 41)
  - Decorations and Degrees (Box 41)
    - Decorations and Degrees (Box 41)
    - Distinguished Service Medal - Posthumous award to E.M.W. 8 June 1945 (Box 41)
  - Eufala, Alabama (birthplace) (Box 41)
  - Family - General Watson (Box 42)
    - Garrett, John P. (Box 42)
    - Bullock, Clayton (Box 42)
    - Garrett, Percy, E. (Box 42)
  - Family - Mrs. Watson
    - Cartan, Fred Nash (Box 42)
    - Clarke, Richard W. (Box 42)
    - Crofoot's (Box 42)
    - Myer's, George W. (Box 42)
    - Nash's (Box 42)
  - Friends
    - Solicitude (Box 42)
    - Bloedorn, Walter A. (Box 42)
    - Burdett, William C. (Box 42)
    - Carey, Julia and Joseph (Box 42)
    - Cudahy, Edward A. (Box 42)
    - Davis, William Thornwall (Box 42)
    - Gibson, Hugh S. (Box 42)
    - Guest, Mrs. Frederick (Box 42)
    - Patchin, Robert H. (Box 42)
    - Reed, Edward L. (Box 42)
    - Shearer, Mrs. George L. (Box 42)
    - Tuck, W. Hallam (Box 42)
    - Tyson, Carroll (Box 42)
    - Wallace, Herbert (Box 42)
  - Gasoline, government - for personal trips (Box 43)
  - Guns (Box 43)
  - Household
    - Household servants (Box 43)
  - Jewelers - Cartier, Inc., 1939-1942 (Box 43)
  - Kenwood
    - "Kenwood," Albemarle County, Va. (includes photographs) 1935-1945 (Box 43)
  - Martinsville, Va. (childhood)
    - Martinsville cemetery care 1940-1945 (Box 43)
    - Martinsville, Va. 1936-1943 (Box 43)
  - Masons (Box 43)
  - Military Orders received by Edwin M. Watson 1918 (Box 43)
  - Mistaken identity 1933-1944 (Box 43)
  - Monticello (Box 43)
  - Pannill, William, Mrs. 1939-1944 (Box 43)
  - Personal correspondence
    - A-C 1936-1943 (Box 43)
    - D-G 1934-1944 (Box 43)
    - H-L 1934-1945 (Box 44)
    - M 1934-1944 (Box 44)
    - Receipts, business and personal 1938-1944 (Box 44)
    - Retirement - personal official correspondence re (Box 44)
    - N-S 1933-1945 (Box 44)
    - "Stamps" and first-day covers 1935-1945 (Box 44)
    - Swope, Bayard - personal correspondence 1939-1944 (Box 44)
    - T-Z 1935-1945 (Box 44)
  - Personal miscellany of E.M.W. 1920-1943 (Box 44)
  - Personal photographs of E.M.W. and his family (Box 44)
  - Photographs and autographs - requests for 1939-1944 (Box 44)
  - Photographers & sculptors 1939-1945 (Box 44)
  - Presents (Box 45)
  - Salute 1937-1944 (Box 45)
  - Second Division Association (Box 45)
  - Scrapbook material 1933-1940 (Box 45)
  - Speech file 1935-1945 (Box 46)
  - Travel diary kept by Edwin Watson in Europe 1921-1922 (Box 46)
  - Trips, E.M.W.'s personal 1935-1943 (Box 46)
  - Versailes, Treaty - Paris - President's trip to Rome 1918 Dec. - 1919 Jan. (Box 46)
  - Versailles, Treaty - Paris - President's visit to Belgium 1919 June (Box 46)
  - Versailles, Treaty - Col. Watson's service as Chief of Military Section - Papers re 1919 (Box 46)
  - Versailles, Treaty - Paris - Photographs of Wilson's battlefield visit 1919 (Box 46)
  - Versailles, Treaty - Paris - photographs 1919 (Box 46)
  - Mrs. Watson
    - Watson, Frances Nash (Box 47)
    - E.M.W.'s letters to Frances Nash Watson 1935-1945 (Box 47)
  - World War I (Box 47)
- Frances Nash Watson Personal Papers
  - Correspondence, B-W (Box 47)
    F.N.W. with Bernard M. Baruch, 1945-1964; F.N.W. with Robert Jackson, 1941, 1946 and Truman, TLS, includes 2 H.S.
  - Death of General Watson (Box 47)
    Cards from funeral flowers
    Funeral arrangements, obituaries, bills, etc. for General Watson.
  - Death of General Watson 1945-1946 (Box 48)
    Obituaries and copies of letters of sympathy, 1945 West Point Assembly.
  - Letters of Sympathy, A-H (Box 48)
  - Letters of Sympathy, I-Z (Box 49)
  - Felix Frankfurter-Frances Watson Correspondence
    - Felix Frankfurter to F.W. 1945-1946, 10 items. (Box 50)
    - Felix Frankfurter to F.W. 1947-1948, 14 items. (Box 50)
    - Felix Frankfurter to F.W. (Box 50)
      (including: 2 TLS, Harry Truman to F.F.; 2 LS, Robert E. Sherwood to F.F.; 2 LS, Hans Kindler to F.F.; TLS, Henry Morganthau, Jr., to F.W.; 2 TLS, Gilbert H. Montague to F.F.)
    - Felix Frankfurter to Frances Watson 1951-1952, 15 items. (Box 50)
      Including 2 photographs and ALS, Bernard Baruch to F.F.
    - Felix Frankfurter to F.W. 1953-1955, 10 items. (Box 50)
      Including TLS, Martin Agronsky to F.F.; and telegram, Olga Koussevitzky to F.F.
    - Felix Frankfurter to F.W. 1956-1960, 10 items. (Box 50)
    - Felix Frankfurter to F.W. 1961-1964, 12 items. (Box 50)
    - Felix Frankfurter to F.W. n.d., ca. 40 items. (Box 50)
    - Printed materials, by and about Felix Frankfurter, many inscribed by F.F. to Frances Watson (all inscribed items sent to RARE BOOK ROOM) 1945-1965, 15 items. (Box 50)
    - "Clippings of a Political Nature" Scrapbook of clippings re E.M.W. 1932 (Box 50)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Items
    - Programs of Ceremonies dedicating the Home of Franklin D. Roosevelt, Hyde Park, New York as a National Historical Site, April 12, 1946. (Box 50)
    - Invitation to Mr. Nash requesting his presence at the Dedication of the Home of Franklin D. Roosevelt April 12, 1946 (Box 50)
    - Program, State Visit of Their Britannic Majesties June 1939 (Box 50)
    - Program, A Thanksgiving Day Service, The White House November 26, 1942 (Box 50)
    - Program, The Order of the Service for Saturday, March 4, 1944, 10:30 A.M. on the Eleventh Anniversary of the Inauguation of Franklin D. Roosevelt. April 12, 1946 (Box 50)
    - Program, Jefferson Day Dinner April 13, 1945 (Box 50)
    - Press release, State Visit of their Britannic Majesties June 1939 (Box 50)
    - Silver playing-card holder, with E.M.W. initials, and emblem, "President Franklin D. Roosevelt, Hyde Park, N.Y." (Box 51)
    - Leather calling-card container, "E.M.W. from F.D.R. January 30, 1940." (Box 51)
    - Printed survey cards, "Which one of the following would you like to see nominated for President of the U.S. in 1940?" (Box 51)
    - Card index of E.M.W.'s West Point classmates (Box 51)
- Oversize Items
  - Invitation to E.M.W. to participate in the annual Pilgrimmage to the Alamo on the occasion of the laying of flowers at the Shrine of Texas Liberty Monday, April 17, 1939
  - Invitation to E.M.W. to participate in the annual Pilgrimmage to the Alamo Monday, April 21, 1941
  - Invitation to E.M.W. to participate in the annual Pilgrimmage to the Alamo Monday, April 22, 1940
  - Wisdom, 28th issue, limited edition, w/photograph of Felix Frankfurter on cover and article, "From the wisdom of ...." 1959 January
    Inscribed on cover, "Dear Frances Xmas 1959-Affectionately Felix")
  - Photograph of head of Felix Frankfurter sculpted by S. Platt
  - Clippings re Frances Nash 1917-1919
  - 2 scrapbooks with clippings chiefly re the President
  - War Bond drive phonograph record
  - 2 photograph albums